Guide to the Miguel A. de Capriles Papers MC 60
New York University Archives
Miguel A. de Capriles Papers
1920-1972
MC 60
New York University Archives
2.71 linear feet
Miguel A. de Capriles received his B.A., M.A. and J.D. from NYU and served in various positions within the University from 1935-1976, including Law Professor, Director of the Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning, Dean of the School of Law, Vice President and General Counsel of the University. This collection contains his personal diaries from 1920 to 1972, and papers for conferences pertaining to corporate law.
Capriles, Miguel Angel de
Arrangement note
Folders are arranged chronologically. The files are grouped into 2 series: I. Diaries II. Academic Papers
Biographical/Historical note
Miguel (Mike) Angel de Capriles was born on November 30, 1906, in Mexico City. His family moved to the United States in 1920, and he graduated from the High School of Commerce in New York City in 1924. In 1924 de Capriles began a long and prolific association with NYU that would last until 1974, when he enrolled as an undergraduate at Washington Square College. Graduating cum laude with a B.S. in 1927, he became an Administrative Officer and an instructor in the Economics Department following his graduation. In 1931 de Capriles received an M.A. in Economics, and in 1935 he received a J.D. from the School of Law. He married Dorothy W. Hafner, a fellow fencer and NYU School of Law graduate, in 1938.
Except for a brief hiatus from NYU during World War II, when he worked in Washington, D.C., for the Department of Justice, de Capriles served in numerous administrative offices and as a law professor, specializing in corporate law and finance, from 1935 until his retirement in 1974. Among his many positions at the University, he founded the Inter-American Law Institute at NYU in 1947, served as the director of the Office of Institutional Research and Educational Planning from 1953-63, was the Dean of the NYU School of Law from 1964-67, and served as the Vice President and General Counsel of NYU from 1967-74. In 1974, de Capriles was named Distinguished Professor of Law at Hastings College, University of California, San Francisco. He died in San Francisco in 1981 at the age of 75.
De Capriles was also a world-renowned fencer, having taken up the sport as an undergraduate at NYU. Ranked consistently as one of the top ten fencers in the US from 1935-51, de Capriles won 10 national individual fencing titles during his career. He was also a member of the U.S. Olympic Fencing Team from 1932-52, winning two bronze metals (1932 in epée and 1948 in saber). He continued to be actively involved in fencing after his retirement from competition in 1952, serving as president of the International Fencing Federation and working with the U.S. Olympic committee. He is a member of the NYU Sports Hall of Fame.
Sources:
Miguel Angel de Capriles Biographical File. NYU Archives.
Scope and Contents note
Series I: Contains address books and diaries from 1920, when de Capriles arrived in the US, until 1972, two years before his retirement from NYU. The documents contain both personal and professional information regarding events, appointments, brief notes, and the names and addresses of friends and colleagues.
Series II: Consists of three academic papers on the topic of corporate law published or presented in the late 1960s and early 1970s.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection. Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted. Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science.; United States Olympic Association.; Corporation law.; Diaries.; Fencing.; New York University |x Administration.; New York University |x Athletics.; New York University. Inter-American Law Institute.; New York University. School of Law.
- Diaries, 1920-1972
  - Address Book, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Books, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diary, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diary, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Diary, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Diary, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Diary, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Academic Papers, DeCapriles, Miguel
  - Paper on Judge Fuld, 1946-1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Paper on Business Corporations, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Paper on Corporate Management, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)